# **Behjat Siddiquie**

Seattle, WA

## Summary

I am an applied researcher with over ten years of industry experience, in Computer Vision and Deep Learning. I have a track record of transforming state-of-the-art research into innovative consumer products and features. At Amazon, I built Computer Vision and Deep Learning based systems that helped launch Amazon Go's cashierless checkout technology in third party stores. These systems have been deployed in over a hundred physical stores worldwide, and serve over fifty million customers annually.

## Experience

Oct. 2018 - current Amazon

Senior Applied Scientist/Tech Lead Manager on the Amazon Go research team

Seattle, WA

- Role: I am a Research Lead at Amazon Go, building technology for cashierless shopping. I lead a number of critical projects, in which I work with the engineering and product leadership to translate business goals into concrete research problems, design the technical roadmap for 4-6 member research teams, mentor team members, lead the execution, and partner with engineering teams to productionize solutions. Selected projects are listed below:
- Improved customer receipt accuracy: Achieved a 30% error reduction in Amazon Go's core receipt generation system by incorporating product context in transformer based customer activity detection models. (2022-23).
- Launched Amazon Go in third party stores: Built, from ground up, a computer vision based system to generate, maintain and update, in real-time, a complete map of product placement in a physical store, which was a pre-requisite to Amazon Go launching in 3rd party stores. This system runs in over a hundred 3rd party stores worldwide and is based on deep learning models for 3D object detection and large-scale product identification. (2018-21).
- Fundamental Research: Led several student intern projects, leading to CVPR/ICCV publications in Generative AI.

May 2016 - Sep. 2018 Amazon

Applied Scientist on the Amazon Go research team

Seattle, WA

• I designed, prototyped and deployed multiple key components of Amazon Go's person tracking system, improving accuracy, reducing costs and enabling Amazon Go to scale up from a single store in early 2018 to over a hundred stores in 2023. I developed deep learning based solutions for object detection, semantic and instance segmentation, person re-identification and multi-task learning.

Oct. 2011 - May 2016 SRI International

Senior Computer Scientist (Mar. 2015 - May 2016); Computer Scientist (Oct. 2011 - Mar. 2015)

Princeton, NJ

- Role: I worked on several CV/ML projects, in various roles, including as a co-Principal Investigator and as a Tech Lead. Selected projects are listed below:
- Developed a software suite for performing real-time human behavior recognition based on gestures, facial expressions and voice, using multi-modal sensors and modeled human interactions with temporal deep networks.
- Developed techniques to use image analytics for enhancing social-media based security applications.
- Co-authored several research grants, which received over \$2M in research funding from DARPA, ONR and AFRL.

#### University of Maryland, College Park, MD, USA

Aug. 2006 - Oct. 2011

Graduate Research Assistant (Advisor: Prof. Larry S. Davis)

College Park, MD

- PhD Thesis: Image Retrieval based on Complex and Descriptive Queries.
- Active, online and incremental learning for visual scene understanding and image classification.
- Activity recognition in high, medium and low-resolution video.
- Research internships at IBM Research (2010) and SRI International (2009).

#### Education

**University of Maryland, College Park** 

PhD in Computer Science (2011); MS in Computer Science (2009)

Aug. 2006 - Oct. 2011 College Park, MD

July 2002 - May 2006

Mumbai, India

Indian Institute of Technology, Bombay

BTech. in Computer Science

## Selected Publications (google scholar)

- Koutilya PNVR, B. Singh, P. Ghosh, **B. Siddiquie** and D. Jacobs, **LD-ZNet: A Latent Diffusion Approach for Text-Based Image Segmentation**, (ICCV) 2023, (Oral).
- M. Suhail, A. Mittal, B. Siddiquie, C. Broaddus, J. Eledath, G. Medioni and L. Sigal, Energy-Based Learning for Scene Graph Generation, (CVPR) 2021, (nominated for the best paper award).
- M. Amer, T. Shields, B. Siddiquie, A. Tamrakar, A. Divakaran and S. Chai, Deep Multimodal Fusion: A Hybrid Approach, (IJCV) 2018.
- B. Siddiquie, B. White, A. Sharma and L. S. Davis, Multi-Modal Image Retrieval for Complex Queries using Small Codes, (ICMR) 2014.
- M. Amer, B. Siddiquie, C. Richey and A. Divakaran, Emotion Detection in Speech using Deep Networks, (ICASSP) 2014.
- R. Feris, **B. Siddiquie**, J. Petterson, Y. Zhai, A. Datta, L. Brown and S. Pankanti, **Large-Scale Vehicle Detection**, **Indexing**, and **Search in Urban Surveillance Videos**, IEEE Transactions on Multimedia, 2012.
- B. Siddiquie, R. Feris and L. S. Davis, Image Ranking and Retrieval Based on Multi-Attribute Queries, (CVPR) 2011, (Oral).
- B. Siddiquie and A. Gupta, Beyond Active Noun Tagging: Modeling Contextual Interactions for Multi-Class Active Learning, (CVPR) 2010, (Oral).
- A. Kembhavi, B. Siddiquie, R. Miezianko, S. McCloskey and L. S. Davis, Incremental Multiple Kernel Learning for Object Recognition, (ICCV) 2009.

#### **Patents**

- Inferring facility planograms, (Amazon), 11,093,785.
- Image-based detection of planogram product spaces, (Amazon), 11,842,321; 11,810,362.
- Re-identification of agents using image analysis and machine learning, (Amazon), 11,386,306.
- Recognizing salient video events through learning-based multimodal analysis of visual features and audio-based analytics, (SRI), 10,679,063.
- Exploiting multi-modal affect and semantics to assess the persuasiveness of a video, (SRI), 10,303,768.
- Dynamic hybrid models for multimodal analysis, (SRI), 9,875,445.
- Multi-Modal Modeling of Temporal Interaction Sequences, (SRI), 9,734,730.
- Image Ranking Based on Attribute Correlation, (IBM), 8,903,198.
- Object Detection in Crowded Scenes, (IBM), 8,811,663.
- Video based Detection of Multiple Object Types under Varying Poses, (IBM), 8,620,026.
- Multi-View Object Detection using Appearance Model Transfer from Similar Scenes, (IBM), 9,224,046.

#### Technical Skills

Languages: Python, PyTorch, C/C++

### Citizenship

**US Citizen**